Assistant Professor, University of Toronto

https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~sachdeva/ sachdeva@cs.toronto.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Algorithms, and its connections to learning, optimization, and statistics

My research is focused on the design of fast algorithms for problems ranging from theoretical computer science to machine learning and statistics. My work brings together tools from convex optimization, numerical linear algebra, data-structures, and approximation theory.

APPOINTMENTS

University of Toronto

2017 - Present

Assistant Professor, Mathematical and Computational Sciences

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science

Vector Institute, Faculty Affiliate

2019 - Present

Institute for Advanced Study, Visitor

Fall 2019

Google, Research Scientist

2016 - 2017

Yale University, Postdoctoral Associate

2014 - 2016

Supervisor: Prof. Daniel Spielman

UC Berkeley, Simons Research Fellow

Fall 2013

EDUCATION

Princeton University

2008 - 2013

Ph.D., Department of Computer Science

Advisor: Prof. Sanjeev Arora

Indian Institute of Technology Bombay

2004 - 2008

B.Tech., Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Honors and Awards

Invited Plenary Speaker at SODA 2023

Best Paper Award at FOCS 2022

Ontario Early Researcher Award 2022-27 (CAD 150,000)

NSERC Discovery Grant 2018-2023 (CAD 177,500)

MITACS Accelerate Grant 2021 (CAD 65,000)

Connaught New Researcher Award 2018 (CAD 10,000)

Google Faculty Research Award, 2017 (USD 43,335)

Simons-Berkelev Research Fellowship, Fall 2013 (USD 26.466)

Postdoctoral Research Fellowship by Institute for Computational and Experimental Research in Mathematics (2013-2014, USD 50.000 – declined)

President of India Gold Medal for topping the class of 2008 (of 500+ students)

Jayanti Deshmukh Memorial Gold Medal for being the most outstanding B.Tech. student in the computer science class of 2008 (out of 35 students)

Honorable Mention at ACM ICPC World Finals, Tokyo 2007 representing IIT Bombay

1st all over India in IIT Entrance Examination 2004 (among 170,000+ students)

Bronze Medalist at 36th International Chemistry Olympiad (IChO) 2004, Kiel, Germany

Aditya Birla Scholarship 2004–08, awarded to only 10 engineering students each year.

Dhirubai Ambani Scholarship 2004–08, awarded to top 10 students in Maharashtra state

Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana (KVPY) fellowship 2002–04. Awarded to around 50 students each year; aimed at promoting research careers in the sciences.

Monographs

Faster Algorithms via Approximation Theory

S. Sachdeva, N. K. Vishnoi

In Foundations and Trends in Theoretical Computer Science 9.2 (FTTCS) 2014, pp. 125-210

Refereed Journal

Publications

Graph Sparsification, Spectral Sketches, and Faster Resistance Computation via Short Cycle

Decompositions

T. Chu, Y. Gao, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, S. Sawlani, J. Wang

SIAM Journal on Computing, FOCS 2018 Special Issue (2020), pp. 85–157

The mixing time of the Dikin walk in a polytope - A simple proof

S. Sachdeva, N. Vishnoi

In Operations Research Letters, 44.5 (September 2016), pp. 630–634

An Arithmetic Analogue of Fox's Triangle Removal Argument

P. Hatami, S. Sachdeva, M. Tulsiani

In Online Journal of Analytic Combinatorics 11 (OJAC) 2016

Provable ICA with Unknown Gaussian Noise, and Implications for Gaussian Mixtures and Autoencoders

S. Arora, R. Ge, A. Moitra, S. Sachdeva

In Algorithmica 72.1 (May 2015), pp. 215–236

Inapproximability of Minimum Vertex Cover on k-Uniform k-Partite Hypergraphs

V. Guruswami, S. Sachdeva, R. Saket

In SIAM Journal on Discrete Mathematics 29.1 (SIDMA) 2015, pp. 36–58

Greedy Geometric Algorithms for Collection of Balls, with Applications to Geometric Approximation and Molecular Coarse-Graining

F. Cazals, T. Dreyfus, S. Sachdeva, N. Shah

In Computer Graphics Forum 33–6, 2014

On the Characterization and Selection of Diverse Conformational Ensembles with Applications to Flexible Docking

S. Loriot, S. Sachdeva, K. Bastard, C. Prevost, F. Cazals

In Computational Biology and Bioinformatics, IEEE/ACM Transactions on 8.2 (TCBB) 2011, pp. 487–498

REFEREED CONFERENCE / WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS A New Approach to Estimating Effective Resistances & Counting Spanning Trees in Expanders L. Li, S. Sachdeva

In $34^{\rm th}$ ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2023

Maximum Flow and Minimum-Cost Flow in Almost-Linear Time

L. Chen, R. Kyng. Y. P. Liu, R. Peng, M. P. Gutenberg, S. Sachdeva

In 63rd IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS) 2022

Best Paper Award at FOCS 2022

A Convergent and Dimension-Independent Min-Max Optimization Algorithm

V. Keswani, O. Mangoubi, S. Sachdeva, N. K. Vishnoi

In 39th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2022

Nested Dissection Meets IPMs: Planar Min-Cost Flow in Nearly Linear Time

S. Dong, Y. Gao, G. Goranci, Y.T. Lee, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, G. Ye

In 33th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2022

Unifying Width-Reduced Methods for Quasi-Self-Concordant Optimization

D. Adil, B. Bullins, S. Sachdeva

In 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2021

Almost-linear-time Weighted ℓ_p -norm Solvers in Slightly Dense Graphs via Sparsification.

D. Adil, B. Bullins, R, Kyng, S. Sachdeva

In 48nd International Colloquium on Automata, Languages, and Programming (ICALP) 2021

Regularized linear autoencoders recover the principal components, eventually

X. Bao, J. Lucas, S. Sachdeva, R. Grosse

In 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2020

Faster Graph Embeddings via Coarsening

M. Fahrbach, G. Goranci, S. Sachdeva, R. Peng, C. Wang

In 37th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2020

Faster p-norm minimizing flows, via smoothed q-norm problems

D. Adil, S. Sachdeva

In 31th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2020

Fast, Provably convergent IRLS Algorithm for p-norm Linear Regression

D. Adil, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva

In 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2019

Which Algorithmic Choices Matter at Which Batch Sizes? Insights From a Noisy Quadratic Model

G. Zhang, L. Li, Z. Nado, J. Martens, S. Sachdeva, G. Dahl, C. Shallue, R. Grosse

In 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2019

Flows in Almost Linear Time via Adaptive Preconditioning

R. Kyng, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, D. Wang

In 51st ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2019

Improved Semi-Supervised Learning with Multiple Graphs

K. Viswanathan*, S. Sachdeva*, A. Tomkins, S. Ravi (*=equal contribution)

In 22nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2019

Iterative Refinement for ℓ_p -norm Regression

D. Adil, R. Kyng, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva

In 30th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2019

Short Cycles via Low-Diameter Decompositions

Y. P. Liu, S. Sachdeva, Z. Yu

In 30th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2019

Graph Sparsification, Spectral Sketches, and Faster Resistance Computation, via Short Cycle Decompositions

T. Chu, Y. Gao, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, S. Sawlani, J. Wang

In 59th IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS) 2018

Invited to SIAM Journal on Computing Special Issue

Invited to Highlights of Algorithms 2019

Convergence Results for Neural Networks via Electrodynamics

R. Panigrahy, A. Rahimi, S. Sachdeva, Q. Zhang

In 9th Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science (ITCS) 2018

 $Near-optimal\ approximation\ algorithm\ for\ simultaneous\ Max-Cut$

A. Bhangale, S. Khot, S. Kopparty, S. Sachdeva, D. Thiruvenkatachari

In 29th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2018

Sampling Random Spanning Trees Faster than Matrix Multiplication

D. Durfee, R. Kyng, J. Peebles, A. B. Rao, S. Sachdeva

In 49th ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2017

A framework for analyzing resparsification algorithms

R.Kyng, J. Pachocki, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva

In 28th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2017

Approximate Gaussian Elimination for Laplacians: Fast, Sparse, and Simple

R. Kyng, S. Sachdeva

In 57th IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science (FOCS) 2016

Invited to Highlights of Algorithms 2017

Sparsified Cholesky and Multigrid Solvers for Connection Laplacians

R. Kyng, Y. T. Lee, R. Peng, S. Sachdeva, and D. A. Spielman

In 48th ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2016

Fast, Provable Algorithms for Isotonic Regression in all ℓ_p -norms

R. Kyng, A. B. Rao, S. Sachdeva

In 29th Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2015

Algorithms for Lipschitz Learning on Graphs

R. Kyng, A. B. Rao, S. Sachdeva, D. A. Spielman

In 28th Conference on Learning Theory (COLT) 2015

Simultaneous Approximation of Constraint Satisfaction Problems

A. Bhangale, S. Kopparty, S. Sachdeva

In 42nd International Colloquium on Automata, Languages, and Programming (ICALP) 2015

Optimal Inapproximability for Scheduling Problems via Structural Hardness for Hypergraph Vertex Cover

S. Sachdeva, R. Saket

In 28th IEEE Conference on Computational Complexity (CCC) 2013

Approximating the Exponential, the Lanczos Method and an $\widetilde{O}(m)$ -Time Spectral Algorithm for Balanced Separator

L. Orecchia, S. Sachdeva, N. K. Vishnoi

In 44th ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2012

Provable ICA with Unknown Gaussian Noise, and Implications for Gaussian Mixtures and Autoencoders

S. Arora, R. Ge, A. Moitra, S. Sachdeva

In 26th Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2012

Invited to Algorithmica Special Issue for Machine Learning

Finding Overlapping Communities in Social Networks: Towards a Rigorous Approach

S. Arora, R. Ge, S. Sachdeva, G. Schoenebeck

In 13th ACM Conference on Electronic Commerce (EC) 2012

Testing Permanent Oracles — Revisited

S. Arora, A. Bhattacharyya, R. Manokaran, S. Sachdeva

In 16th International Workshop on Randomization and Computation (RANDOM) 2012

Nearly Optimal NP-Hardness of Vertex Cover on k-Uniform k-Partite Hypergraphs

S. Sachdeva, R. Saket

In 14th International Workshop on Approximation Algorithms for Combinatorial Optimization Problems (APPROX) 2011

THESES

New Results in the Theory of Approximation: Fast Graph Algorithms and Inapproximability Ph.D. Thesis, Princeton University, 2013. Advised by Sanjeev Arora

On the Hardness of Approximating Vertex Cover

B.Tech. Thesis, IIT Bombay, 2008. Advised by Sundar Vishwanathan

SUPERVISION

Graduate students:

Deepkamal Kaur Gill (MScAC student, UToronto, 2022–)

Lawrence Li (Ph.D. student, UToronto, 2020–)

Yibin Zhao (Ph.D. student, UToronto, 2020–)

Hao Zhang (MScAC student, UToronto, 2021–22)

Deeksha Adil (M.Sc. student, UToronto, 2017–2019, Ph.D. student, 2019–2022)

Postdocs:

Gramoz Goranci (2020–2021). Assistant Professor at U. Glasgow.

Undergraduate students:

Anvith Thudi (UToronto, 2022-)

Devansh Ranade (UToronto, 2020–2021)

Jack McKinney (UToronto, Summer 2020)

Zejun Yu (UToronto, Summer 2018)

Mentees:

Yang P. Liu (Summer 2018). Graduate student, Stanford.

Joshua Wang (Summer 2017). Research Scientist, Google.

Qiuyi (Richard) Zhang (Fall 2016). Software Engineer, Google.

Xiao Shi (Fall 2015). Software Engineer, Facebook.

Talks

Almost-linear time Algorithms for Max-Flow and More

10th Anniversary Symposium, Simons Institute for Theory of Computing, May 2022

Theory Seminar, University of Toronto, May 2022

Theory Seminar, University of Texas Austin, Apr 2022

Theory Seminar, University of Waterloo, Mar 2022

Algorithms and Complexity Seminar, IRIF Paris, Mar 2022

Improved ℓ_p -norm Optimization via Iterative Refinement

Theory Seminar, University of Washington, Seattle, Apr 2021

Theory Seminar, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, Feb 2021

Seminar, Indian Institute of Technology, Mumbai, Sep 2019

Seminar, Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi, Sep 2019

Theory Seminar, Northwestern, Evanston, Feb 2019

Theory Seminar, UChicago / TTIC, Chicago, Feb 2019

STOCA Workshop, Google Mountain View, Feb 2019

Faster p-norm minimizing flows, via smoothed q-norm problems

Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA), Salt Lake City, Jan 2020

Fast IRLS Algorithms for p-norm regression

Fuji Co-creation Lab, University of Toronto, May 2020

Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, Nov 2019

Theory Seminar, Yale University, Nov 2019

Graph Sparsifiers via Short-Cycle Decompositions

Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, Dec 2019

Highlights of Algorithms, Copenhagen, Jun 2019

Approximate Gaussian Elimination and Applications

Laplacian 2.0 Workshop, FOCS 2018, Paris, Oct 2018

Fast Approximate Gaussian Elimination for Laplacians

High Performance Graph Algorithms, Dagstuhl Seminar, Germany, Jun 2018

Canada Applied and Industrial Mathematics Society (CAIMS), Toronto, Jun 2018

Department Seminar, University of Waterloo, Nov 2017

Highlights of Algorithms, Berlin, Jun 2017

Simons Collaboration on Algorithms & Geometry, New York, Mar 2017

TOCA-SV, Stanford, Nov 2016

TCS Plus Seminar, Sep 2016

Theory of Computation Seminar, Harvard University, Sep 2016

Theory Lunch, Boston University, Sep 2016

Fast Algorithms for Optimization and Learning on Graphs

Google, New York, May 2016

Computer Science Colloquium, Purdue University, Apr 2016

Department of Computer Science Lecture, University of Toronto, Canada, Mar 2016

Computer Science Seminar, University of Colorado Boulder, Mar 2016

Regression on Graphs - Lipschitz and Isotonic

Simons Seminar, University of Texas Austin, May 2016

University of Chicago, Scientific and statistical computing seminar, Nov 2015

Lipschitz Learning on Graphs

Theory seminar, CS Department, Carnegie Mellon University, Nov 2016

IIT Bombay, CS department seminar, Jul 2015

EPFL (École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne) INF department seminar, Jul 2015

Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), Paris, Jul 2015

UC San Diego, CS department theory seminar, May 2015

Yale University, Statistics department seminar, Apr 2015

Triangle Removal in Groups

Simons Institute, UC Berkeley, Real analysis seminar, Nov 2013

Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) Computer science/discrete mathematics seminar, Apr 2013

Generalizations of KKL Theorem and Friedgut's Junta Theorem

Simons Institute, UC Berkeley, Real analysis workshop, Aug 2013

Hardness for Scheduling Problems

Conference on Computational Complexity (CCC), Palo Alto, Jun 2013

Near-linear Time Algorithms for Balanced Separator

Rutgers University, DIMACS/CS theoretical computer science seminar, Mar 2013

University of Washington, ETP theory connections, Aug 2012

Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC), New York, May 2012

Institute for Advanced Study (IAS) Computer science/discrete mathematics seminar, Apr 2012

Testing Permanent Oracles

International Workshop on Randomization and Computation (RANDOM), Boston, Aug 2012

Professional Service

Editor:

ACM Transactions of Algorithms (TALG) SODA 2021 special issue SIAM Journal on Computing (SICOMP) STOC 2019 special issue

Program Committee:

European Symposium on Algorithms (ESA) 2022

Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2022

ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA) 2021

Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC) 2019

Organizer:

Workshop 'Laplacians 2.0', FOCS 2018, Paris, France

Conference Reviewing: STOC (2014–2020), FOCS (2014–2021), SODA (2012–2020), CCC 2020, COLT 2018–2019, ESA 2019, NeurIPS / NIPS (2016–2021), ICML (2018–2020), ITCS (2013, 2020), ICLR 2018, ICALP (2012, 2018–2019), APPROX (2013, 2017), RANDOM (2019, 2014), WADS 2017, SPAA 2017, FSTTCS (2011, 2013), LATIN 2012, QIC 2015

Journal Reviewing: Siam Journal on Discrete Mathematics (SIDMA), Algorithmica, Theory of Computing, Siam Journal on Computing (SICOMP)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Assistant Professor, University of Toronto

Instructor for CSC 2240H: Graphs, Matrices, and Optimization

Fall 2022

Instructor for CSC 263H5: Data Structures and Analysis

Winter 2018-2021

Instructor for CSC 373H5: Algorithm Design and Analysis

Fall 2020, Fall 2022

Instructor for CSC 2421H: Graphs, Matrices, and Optimization

Fall 2018, Winter 2021

Instructor for CSC 2421H: Fast Algorithms via Continuous Methods

Fall 2017

Lecturer, Yale University

Lecturer for CPSC 665: An Algorithmist's toolkit

Spring 2015

Designed and taught a full course on advanced algorithms (2 lectures a week) 55% of students rated the course excellent (highest rating)

Teaching Assistant, Princeton University

Assistant in Instruction for COS 433: Cryptography Spring 2010 Assistant in Instruction for COS 340: Reasoning About Computation Fall 2009

Professional EXPERIENCE

Toyota Technological Institute

Chicago, IL Summer 2012 Research Intern. Supervisor: Yury Makarychev

Microsoft Research India Bangalore, India

Research Intern. Supervisor: Nisheeth K. Vishnoi Summer 2011

INRIA Sophia-Antipolis, France

Summer 2007 Research Intern. Supervisor: Frederic Cazals

Zurich, Switzerland

Summer 2006 Research Intern. Supervisor: Riko Jacob